so these are some questions
that come from all around the world
and i'll start with this first one and
it's in terms of persistence
in practice
and a friend asks
how important is having a fixed routine
does it have does it have a big impact
on dhamma
progress producing wholesome actions
mental qualities
or it doesn't really matter much
should you have persistence or can you
just well like think yeah yeah so uh
well like think yeah yeah so uh
it depends on every individual
so if there is a person
with a with with tendencies of complete
kind of
disorganization laziness
cannot adhere to basic worldly routine
or discipline
then yeah it's very helpful
just to you know get your mind in a
certain sense of responsibility and
stick into the
sticking to the training uh but then you
have the other
type of an individual that
would be pretty much
holding the view that training routine
and being methodical precise
is the training is the development of
dhamma which it isn't
it's just an external phone so you have
to see which individual you are
and if you are the the former then yeah
get some routine
to keep you in check if you're the
latter then maybe you know
become more kind of less routine based
and experience that
you know mind sort of floating away
without having anything fixed to do
or to adhere to because either way
that's not the dhamma
so the reflections you should be making
on the level of practice of dhamma
the accomplishment in virtue that's not
a method that's not a routine that comes
with insight
and repetition in the training and
sustaining the effort
if the routine helps you for that you do
it
but sometimes the routine can take place
instead of that
and all you and your stuff you all have
to do is the routine and i'm practicing
the dhamma
i just get up at this do this do this do
this i finish the day success it's a
success it's a successful day because i've
it's a successful day because i've
successfully completed my routine
right that's not how the progress and
down is measured
so and you might be kind of in between
so you start with a routine but then
keep yourself in check in case you start
taking routine
in that in that kind of mechanical sense
whereby as i said i just need to go through a
as i said i just need to go through a
routine and then i'll be anxiety free
and worry free because i've completed my
duty so if you're taking it as a duty it's
so if you're taking it as a duty it's
not the dhamma it's not the virtue
anymore it's the external projection of it
it's the external projection of it
because you can become like a an
a robot you know it's unaware of exactly
exactly that's the risk of it
always but sometimes you can be too
loose and sometimes you can be too tight
so you can't just say yes routines are
always good because somebody might be
already too tight and too externally
projected on the sense of duty
and observances and stuff that they do
in which case no they need to loosen up
actually these routines
to get that sense of whoa my mind my
responsibility my choice my intention
uh but then you have the other
individual who's too loose
which is absolutely and equally no sense
of responsibility or intentions because
it's too loose
nothing's taken internally taken on
uh so then yeah they would need some
external adherence to the certain you know
adherence to the certain you know
routines and principles
just you know get them a bit into into
into shape
and again in terms of persistence
you know just you persistently for
example keeping the precepts
keeping the precepts
sure you just you have to build
it up anyway yes exactly like people can
take people can take persistence to mean i'll
people can take persistence to mean i'll
just you know
adhere to determination and persist
that's one way of persistence sure
but persistence is exactly that like it
can be
much more relaxed yet still persistent
like you don't have specific
determination to adhere to do
but at the same time you don't do
certain actions you are not going
against the precepts so you are
persistent you are persistently maintaining and
you are persistently maintaining and
protecting the basis
of your virtue that in return protects
the basis of your mind
so sometimes if you feel you're getting
looser maybe you need to
you know build up some determination or
something but not as a rule of thumb
like i always must have
this this persisting determination and
focus no because sometimes that that that can
no because sometimes that that that can
be the reason for you not seeing where
the practice is it's
too tight and that often you know the
similarity that woulda gave
the the the loot strings like you want
to play the music with them
but you will not be able to play the
music if the strings are too tight
or too loose so you need to find the
right balance
so if you are one who is
really trying at least you're really
trying and you're persisting and you feel there
and you're persisting and you feel there
is some
you know development at least you know
calmness and
dispassion and then
you fail you make a mistake you break a
precept now you just you know it feels like
now you just you know it feels like
all all your work is kind of lost
sometimes is it
is that the case you think what's the
attitude then for that person because
you can really well yeah now the mind
tries to go the other way exactly
it's really messed up now yeah well it
depends uh
depends what what priest we broke to
what extent
how much and so on yeah
if it's like those serious presets of
killing or something like that then yeah
maybe you have messed up
but if it's not on that level then yeah
you messed up but not in a sense of
that you cannot grow out of it now
as in you messed up sure you reckon is
the mistake
and now you basically be even more aware
next time but it's good actually
like i know the mind can fall into that
trap of like
uh negativity about oh i messed up it's
i'm worthless and all
that and you have to endure it because
that's pretty much the result of you
messing up so don't just try to like
oh you know i should not think these
thoughts
because feeling bad about messing up
when you were actually intentionally
messed up
and broke the precepts will as i said
make you more mindful next time if you
don't try to negate
that bad feeling and allow it to endure
as long as it lasts
so basically you're taking a more weight
off your action of messing up
through and during that pain which is a
result of you messing up
so then then
as you pick up your precepts again when
the when the challenges come well the the
when the challenges come well the the
memory of pain will be fresh
pain of i was when i chose to break the
presets so then you will not necessarily do it
so then you will not necessarily do it
so easily
pain of regret exactly the remorse the
most the most guilt can be very useful sure
the most guilt can be very useful sure
can be irrational in which case you have
to be aware of that as well
and not unnecessarily feel it have i
done anything wrong
yes okay then then there is a base for
guilt and maybe i should endure it a bit
sometimes you just feel guilty but have
i done i don't know okay now it's
irrational and now i shall not fuel it either way
and now i shall not fuel it either way
you'll probably have to undo it
there's that um for example okay so
that that inner voice there was that one
question what you should do should you do about
what you should do should you do about
it in a critical inner critic yeah
so i think that that actually goes
exactly there well
as i said you messed up you messed up
really messed up real bad idiot whatever
it is
never make it well
as as painful as that is you need to
recognize that pretty much all of those
mental states
in a critic sense of guilt whatever else
your mind is revolving on
are the symptoms of the problem they are
the results
so you don't want to just see them as a
problem and then oh how do i stop the
inner critic
no you actually see inner critic as an
indicator of a problem that you're not seeing
of a problem that you're not seeing
because the the power that that inner
critic that your own mind has
is the power you've been sort of feeding
it through certain other actions that
you're not aware of
and same when like people have this
irrational guilt constantly or
irrational critic or something
it's the symptom of basically when those
things are not present
off your actions of your actions and
choices so in other words you endured in a
so in other words you endured in a
critic don't act out of it
don't feed it don't argue with it either
but then when inner critic goes away
then you keep an eye on your choices and
things you do
and things you think and things you
allow your mind to revolve around
because that's how you're providing fuel
for the inner critic later on
in other words when inner critic is not
there the lack of awareness in
in regard to wholesomeness of your
choices actions thoughts themes that you
actions thoughts themes that you
entertain
the lack of awareness there it's pretty
much a um a way of undermining yourself
a um a way of undermining yourself
in a sense of when the inner critic
comes you are completely at its mercy
you have no
you can't say no stop it to your own
mind so you just have to endure it
because you put yourself in that
position and you you can start to see the
and you you can start to see the
connection between your behavior your
choices the mental themes throughout the
day things you do things you say
if if if you start seeing inner critic
or that irrational guilt
or whatever else your mind revolves
around in these negative states see that
as a symptom
don't just try to get rid of that but
say no no no this
is the result something else i do when
this is not present
and when you start looking in that
broader sense the connection between the
two will become apparent because that's
the main thing people don't see the
connection they don't see the connection between
they don't see the connection between
day-to-day behavior and their own
liability to suffer on account of their own mind
to suffer on account of their own mind
because for that virtue training
reflection all that's required
repetitively you need to keep doing it
and wisdom would be the result of it
when you start seeing the connection and
then you know for yourself
you don't need to take it on faith that
a good behavior
restrained speech restrained mind will
result in the well-being of your mind kind of
in the well-being of your mind kind of
makes sense
but until you see the connection
directly you will be taking it on faith
which is fine
as long as it makes you make the right
effort but the point is will come if you
are making that effort that you're going
to see it for yourself
yeah by basically keeping an eye on my
behavior virtues uh wholesome as well like you
virtues uh wholesome as well like you
know you might not be breaking the
precepts but you're engaging in
pointless chit chat
gossip idol talk you know a bit of
slander a bit of a bad mouth
in this bit of that you know
occasionally seeking distractions
unnecessarily basically you are still
not restrained as you should be
and you're maintaining these unwholesome
themes in your mind
that then you know you're literally
keeping your mind wild
to that extent so when that wild mind
decides to go his own way
starts criticizing barking at you like a
mad dog
well you kept it mad you you kept it
untrained so now you have to endure it's barking
so now you have to endure it's barking
and trying to bite you every now and
then so when it comes down you better start
so when it comes down you better start
training it
you you have developed that uh in that
inner voice
that that mean there is you were
inadvertently feeding it and keeping it wild to that
feeding it and keeping it wild to that
extent
so yes this needs to be dealt with the
inner voice
the inner critic the inner guilt tripper
but it's actually the problem it's not
in that behavior that's the result
of an underlying problem that i've been
inadvertently uh not solving such as you were keeping
uh not solving such as you were keeping
it wild
through allowing it to uncontrollably go
and do things and
and so on and that that's also something
that i mean myself i found that
uh when say going into a very extreme
solitude you get to see that inner voice very
you get to see that inner voice very
quickly
yeah you know when you've got no
distractions you get you get to see that
inner voice very
very quickly and it takes a while
to come down yeah yeah and what's the
difference there
the difference is the environment of uh
distraction yeah there was none so exactly so
yeah there was none so exactly so
without a distraction he becomes
apparent now because
then see if if a wild dog or a semi-wild
dog has his distractions he won't bark at
has his distractions he won't bark at
you
he will not try to to bite you and
harass you you take away the
distractions it's going to start complaining yeah and
it's going to start complaining yeah and
that's exactly what the mind does when
you take it into solitude
but i also remember also in my own
experience that
going into solitude
and then that inner voice becoming very
apparent it was also very irritating you know
it was also very irritating you know
what i mean you were reversed to it yeah
i was
wow i i don't i don't like this person
and yet i'm with this person 24 7.
and you're ignoring even your own
aversion towards it because you were
you were being distracted through
allowing distraction for it
so keeping yourself equally oblivious
um and that's the important bit you know
you get to see these things in solitude
and sooner or later you have to come out
of the solitude and then realize but i
don't need to go back all the way to the
distractions i can come out of the extreme solitude
i can come out of the extreme solitude
or not necessarily live
perpetually in the extreme solitude but
that's still not an excuse for me to now
allow this animal to go back to these
distractions and become wild again
and that's exactly the work that's the
training that's the guiding of the
senses if the animal is tamed
and you protect it from the unwholesome
you know debates we spoke about
which is always your responsibility it's
never that never can
the choice is to accept the distraction
to accept last aversion
can never come from the environment
those choices are always yours
environment can provide you with hooks
and baits but you are the one
always every single time responsible for
choosing it
and the more you become aware of that
inner voice the more you practice
solitude and then you go out you start
to see that responsibility so you
realize yeah i can actually this is a good
yeah i can actually this is a good
balance between solitude
like non-extreme solitude and some
degrees of solitude and so on
um and then you realize okay so i just
all i need to do is just protect
these animal this animal not feeding
distractions lust and aversion
and and then there is no basis for it to
be barking at you and attacking you
because it's still calm it's not being
agitated by things you allow it to agitate
by things you allow it to agitate
there's also
i mean when i saw that the inner voice
that i wasn't liking was a complaining
voice and whenever when when there was
no distraction
that was clear that my mind was just
complaining all the time
about everything there was nothing to it
yeah all the time but i never noticed
how much it was doing
right right right yeah i mean it was
just all the time and see
all of that all of that energy behind
all that complaining
has been generated cultivated the
wildness of that animal has been
maintained through the choices of distraction
through the choices of distraction
aversion lust
you know not even major sort of you know
lust or desires or something
but still on a day-to-day basis you kept
your mind that animal you were allowing
it to be sort of distracted
dependent on the external sense objects
one way or the other
and when that's taken away he was left
with that aversion now of complaining
attacking barking being a nuisance
but if you didn't allow that animal to
become distracted there will be no basis
for its
complaining because it can't come down
so whether it's in a critic complaining
voice uh guilt-tripping voice you realize
uh guilt-tripping voice you realize
that's a symptom
of the choices themes that i cultivate
maintain and i'm careless about
throughout the day when i'm not you know
when the mind is not complaining and so
on yeah
so just basically become more aware of
things you choose
to you know do by body by speech by mind
and really as i said it's not this
external observance of be virtuous be
virtuous there is a direct connection
between every single time you make this
choice and how much whether you
whether you fuel whether you encourage
animal animals wildness
or whether you're taming it through your
choices and if you if you adhere to them rightly
and if you if you adhere to them rightly
it won't take long before you realize
oh it's actually tainted and that's the
thing solitude is a good
indicator isn't it solitude reveals the
symptoms if there are any
yeah you're going that's right that's
exactly why they said if a monk doesn't
develop um doesn't delight in solitude doesn't
um doesn't delight in solitude doesn't
you know
make himself want solitude he'll never
understand the nature of his mind well
why wouldn't he want solitude well
exactly exactly
why would a wild animal not want to
become aware of its wildness because
it's unpleasant
because it's dependent on distractions
and solitude takes those away
so um
in terms of that failure again some
another friend asked i don't know if we
can say anything more on the subject
in terms of failure when you feel like
you've let
others down let's say you fail
fail your degree and feel miserable that
you let your family down
and see very little little hope for the
future so he's quite concerned about or seems
so he's quite concerned about or seems
to be overwhelmed by
letting others down you know well why is
that a problem
yeah it's because it's unpleasant
so it it feels unpleasant here and now
when others are disappointed with you
and that's why it's a problem for you
because say you have you have a person
you don't care about
you don't even know and they just stop
you in the street and say
i'm really disappointed in you
you wouldn't really care you might want
to curious to find out why but
who is this person to be disappointed
with me anyway so you want to recognize
that the problem is you don't really
want the pain of it
but if you don't want to pain of it you
should have been careful with your
ambitions beforehand
because each time you want to achieve
something attain something get something
there is a liability you have to take
responsibility for it like you might not
succeed to that extent
and i'm not saying you shouldn't be
ambitious i'm just saying don't take it
for granted but take responsibility for
it because
if you keep the possibility of failure
in your mind well
the disappointment of others will
already be implicit in that and it will
not surprise you or overwhelm you
so given that now you're overwhelmed
pretty much you have to endure the pain
it can't it won't last forever
when the pain fades away reconsider your
ambition find something else if you want
to be ambitious about it do it
but don't just sort of blindly commit to
it
and forget that yeah you might not
succeed and and you know
also fundamentally others can always
find reasons to be disappointed with you
so that's another thing perhaps you
should reevaluate
pleasing others how far you want to go
with that
because you know if you start going that
way it is endless
you can never please others because they
would always have opinions and views and
everything so sure you don't ignore you know others
so sure you don't ignore you know others
in that sense but especially you know
family people you live with
but at the same time the point will come
where you do need to draw some sort of
line for yourself and for others as like well
for yourself and for others as like well
yeah but this is my life and my choices
my responsibility my results
and then accept you know the nagging or
being upset or whatever as part of that
you don't need to have ill will on
account of that either
but if you are not clear with yourself
well you will not be clear in regard to where
you will not be clear in regard to where
that line is and then
when people praise you or blame you you
just well exactly you will you will not
be able to sort of withstand it
without losing perspective so see now
feels like oh it's all and there's
something but it's
it's not i'm sure that person has
experienced this
others being disappointed with them
before in regard to something something else
in regard to something something else
and it came
and it went so you don't need to
completely dismiss it but you certainly
shouldn't be like oh i must be
pleasing others because even that it's
rooted just because you don't want to
suffer when you feel like i must please others
when you feel like i must please others
it's because it's too unpleasant for me
when others are displeased for me uh
with me
and again that's a that's impossible to
achieve like if you think you can avoid the pain
like if you think you can avoid the pain
because of what others by preventing or
providing others with what they want
you're just going to suffer more as the
in that one suitor the buddha says it
nobody is
fully blamed fully blamed or fully
praised nobody's praised all the time
or blamed all the time even the target
was blamed
um and and even the boys people are
sometimes praised
you have to accept that and accept that
really the issue with that is like
again you don't lose perspective yes i
failed maybe i could have done better i shall
maybe i could have done better i shall
try and do better
but don't become irrational about it in
a sense of
oh but but they're so disappointing
because that's actually not about
others it's about you not wanting the
unpleasantness of it
so you think by managing and providing
others where they want
you can avoid this dukkha that you have
to endure but no the only way to avoid
the dukkha that you can endure
is that your enduring is by enduring it
and taking responsibility for it
and not trying to manage the external
world in account to get rid of that
which you reversed it
so that's really the problem the problem
of others being disappointed the problem
of others blaming you or something
is that just feels painful and you don't
want to deal with that pain
sometimes they have a point sometimes
they don't and if you want to maintain
that perspective
you have to accept what you're feeling
on account of others not try to get rid
of it
and see by accepting the pain you will
also not have ill will towards them
because you're not trying to get rid of
dukkha you accept responsibility for it
you're enduring it you're seeing it for
what it is so there's no aversion
towards it
and then you get to see what they're
complaining what they're upset what
they're disappointed about is like
actually yeah they have a point
and from that perspective you will get
to actually act accordingly and upgrade
your behavior
but also sometimes you'll see no they're
completely rational
they just want they just want what they
want they don't really even care about
this they just want what they want
and in that case you will not entertain
that and feed that further
you'll not be angry about it either but
you will certainly be able to
remain unmovable
how to cultivate a sense of urgency
as a lay person
what would be a practical approach to
find motivation
to make dhamma practice a priority as a
lay person
well incessant reflection on the nature
of your situation
you need to make the effort you don't
think about it the mind forgets drifts
away gets pulled with sensuality you
lose sense of urgency
so you have to think about things that
you are subjected to in that world
so you know sometimes might be like a
little prompt sometimes you might just
have to sit and dwell on
everything that could go wrong and they
will bring you with anxiety and sense of
urgency if you already have it you don't need to
if you already have it you don't need to
dwell on these things but if you
wanted that that kind of a bit of a that
sharpness to it because otherwise you
can't move towards the direction of
dhamma at all
sensuality is too overwhelming then yeah
i'm sure things would have happened to
everyone in their life things that they
don't want to think about
so think about that because it can
happen again i think about the fact that
liability to suffering your priority is
sensuality and not dhamma and you you're struggling
and not dhamma and you you're struggling
to get out you're completely trapped
but again like when centrality comes
they will not necessarily feel
the sense of urgency to restrain
themselves so you need to dwell on it you need to
so you need to dwell on it you need to
sustain that context that will keep
things urgent
because always whoever asked their
question they recognize that
when they lose the urgency they kind of
go back to sensuality and lose the
practice and yeah that is not uncommon and even
and yeah that is not uncommon and even
in the sutures the buddha they cut
the buddha would basically scare monks
slide the fire on them
by reminding them what's still there so
they get the sense of urgency because
what i said because they still have work
to do
so they just got negligent so you have
to find something and then
yeah cultivate it when it runs out find
another thing
they will bring a bit of anxiety and
sense of urgency so that you can
actually sustain your precepts and
practice towards that
don't wait till it's too late don't wait
until the world actually throws
something at you
they will fill you with anxiety and fear
and be too much to handle so
start preparing yourself and training
yourself for it
already and you can as i said just just
choose the right themes and
it will it will arise and when you
sickness aging death you know any
basically form of
discomfort suffering you experienced
anything you fear you might
you you would experience anything you
don't experience and you don't think
about it
all of that is all revealing that you're
still liable to these things you're
still liable to be affected by it
think about it and you will feel oh i
need to address this urgently
it would be a natural natural outcome